Guide to the Brown vs. Board of Education Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Brown vs. Board of Education collection
1950-1979
MS 759
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.75
(16 boxes)
Interview notes, correspondence, clippings, copies of court transcripts and briefs assembled by Richard Kluger for his book, Simple Justice: Brown vs. Board of Education. Kluger's interview notes, taken either in person or by mail, with over one hundred people make up the core of the collection. Especially full materials are available for Alexander Bickel, Hugo L. Black, Esther Brown, Linda Brown, John W. Davis, Felix Frankfurter, William H. Hastie, Kenneth B. Clark, Charles H. Houston, Thurgood Marshall, William H. Rehnquist, and Earl Warren. Kluger's copies of the correspondence files of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) relating to this case are also included in the collection, as are two unpublished manuscripts by Phyllis Kluger: an article, "A Short History of Education in the United States," and a book, A Long History of Negro Education.
Kluger, Richard, 1934-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Other Finding Aids
Additional information not yet available in the online version of the finding aid exists in the repository. Contact Manuscripts and Archives for assistance.
Related Material
Richard Kluger Papers (MS 1443). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series, maintaining Kruger's original organization of his research files: I. Subject Files. II. NAACP Legal Defense Fund Correspondence. III. Court Transcripts and Law Review Articles. IV. Sources and Additional Research Materials.
Scope and Contents
The Brown vs. Board of Education Collection consists of the research materials used by Richard Kluger in the preparation of his book,Simple Justice: Brown vs. Board of Education(1976). The book is a history of the Supreme Court decision in that case and the events, social and legal, which preceded it. The collection itself is comprised of interview notes, some correspondence, newspaper and magazine articles, and a large amount of photocopied material such as court transcripts, contemporary newspaper and magazine articles and correspondence from the files of the NAACP Legal Defense Fund. The great strengths of the collection lie in the fact that Kluger has gathered together a great deal of primary source material in the form of interviews with many of the central figures involved in the case. In addition, there are photocopies of correspondence and court transcripts. Subsequent researchers will be greatly aided by the availability of this material in one location.
African Americans -- Education; Education and state; Law; Segregation in education -- Law and legislation -- United States; United States -- Race relations; Adams, Sherman, 1899-1986; Almond, J. Lindsay (James Lindsay), 1898-1986; Bickel, Alexander M.; Black, Charles L., Jr. (Charles Lund), 1915-2001; Black, Hugo LaFayette, 1886-1971; Boulware, Harold R., 1913-; Brown, Esther, 1918-1970; Clark, Kenneth Bancroft, 1914-2005; Clark, Tom C. (Tom Campbell), 1899-1977; Davis, John Anderson, 1924-; Davis, John W. (John Warren), 1888-1980; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Ernst, Morris L. (Morris Leopold), 1888-1976; Figg, Robert McC.; Fortas, Abe, 1910-1982; Frank, John P. (John Paul), 1917-2002; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Franklin, John Hope, 1915-2009; Gardner, Warner W. (Warner Winslow), 1909-2003; Gellhorn, Walter, 1906-1995; Greenberg, Jack, 1924-2016; Harris, Louis, 1921-2016; Hastie, William, 1904-1976; Howe, Louisa Pinkham; Huxman, Walter Augustus, 1887-1972; Kelly, Alfred H. (Alfred Hinsey), 1907-1976; Kiene, Tom Lee, 1906-; Kluger, Phyllis; Kluger, Richard, 1934-; Kreech, David, 1909-; Lewis, Anthony, 1927-2013; Marshall, Thurgood, 1908-1993; Menninger, Karl A. (Karl Augustus), 1893-1990; Minton, Sherman, 1890-1965; Nabrit, James M. (James Madison), 1900-1997; Odum, Howard Washington, 1884-1954; Pollak, Louis H.; Prettyman, E. Barrett (Elijah Barrett), 1891-1971; Rankin, J. Lee, 1907-1996; Robertson, Archibald Gerard, 1889-; Robinson, Spottswood William, III, 1916-1998; Vinson, Fred M., 1890-1953; Vinson, Frederic Moore, 1925-; Waring, Julius Waties, 1880-1968; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974; Wechsler, Herbert, 1909-2000; Weinstein, Jack B., 1921-; Wertham, Fredric, 1895-1981; Wilkins, Roy, 1901-1981; United States. Supreme Court
- Subject Files, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in two sections: Correspondence, Interviews and Individual Files; and Place and Topic Files. The first section consists of letters written in response to Kluger's inquiries; interview notes, both typed and handwritten; newspaper clippings; magazine articles; and photocopies of newspaper and magazine articles. The folders are arranged alphabetically by individual. The materials they contain have been treated as subject material because Kluger used them that way, and their value would be greatly diminished if they were to be removed, or rearranged by type of material.
  The interview notes are among the most valuable materials in the collection. These interviews with Supreme Court Justices, their clerks, NAACP lawyers and other prominent individuals in these cases provide the researcher with a personal view of the individuals interviewed, the events of which they were a part, a view which is not available through other sources. The researcher should recognize, however, that these are notes of interviews and not question and answer transcripts.
  Kluger states in "Sources and Acknowledgements" that some of the interviews were conducted by correspondence; the individuals interviewed in this way are indicated by the notation (C) on his list of "Interviews and Correspondence" contained in the "Sources and Acknowledgements" folder. Fewer than half of the folders contain original correspondence but valuable information can be found in the correspondence of those individuals whom Kluger interviewed by mail. Unfortunately, with very few exceptions, the collection does not contain copies of Kluger's original letters, and in some cases the replies alone may not provide sufficient information for the researcher to judge their importance.
  Significant information can be obtained from the following individual folders: Thurgood Marshall, Earl Warren, Charles H. Houston, William H. Hastie, Kenneth B. Clark, John W. Davis, Linda Brown, Felix Frankfurter, Hugo L. Black, Alexander Bickel, William H. Rehnquist and Esther Brown.
  The second section consists of printed and photocopied material from newspapers, magazines and books as well as travel brochures and maps. The alphabetically arranged folders contain background information on the locations where the various cases originated and organizations and subjects such as the NAACP and Desegregation.
  - Correspondence, Interviews and Individual Files
    - Adams, Sherman (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Almond, J. Lindsay, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bachelder, William K. (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Banks, Lester (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Bell, Derrick (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bickel, Alexander M. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      General note
      See also: box 2, folder 32
    - Bishop, Gardner (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Black, Charles L., Jr. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Black, Hugo L., and Mrs. Black (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Boulware, Harold (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Briggs, Harry (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brown, Esther (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Brown, Inza (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Brown, Linda (Smith) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Burnett, Mrs. McKinley L. (Lena) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Burton, Harold H. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Caliver, Ambrose (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Carter, Robert L. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Clark, Kenneth B. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Clark, Ramsey (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Clark, Tom C. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Coleman, William T., Jr. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Conway, Richard (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Cunningham, William P. (Box 4, Folder 65-67)
    - Croner, Robert and Mary (Spenser) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Davis, John A. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Davis, John W. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - DeLaine, Rev. Joseph A. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Dobie, Armistead (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Douglas, William O. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - DuBois, W. E. B. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Dunne, Gerald T. (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Elman, Philip (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Ernst, Morris (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Fassett, John D. (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Figg, Robert McC. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Flemming, Billie (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Fortas, Abe (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Frank, John P. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Frankfurter, Felix (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Franklin, John Hope (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Gardner, Warner (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Garrett, Henry E. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Gellhorn, Walter (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Greenberg, Jack (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Griffin, Rev. Francis (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Harris, Louis (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Hastie, William H. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Harbaugh, William (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Hawkins, Carl S. (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Hayes, George E.C. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Hill, Herbert (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Hill, Oliver W. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Hinton, James M. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Holland, J.B. (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Howe, Louisa Pinkham (Holt) (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Houston, Charles H. (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
    - Huston, Luther A. (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Huxman, Walter A. (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Indritz, Phineas (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Jackson, Robert H., and William E. Jackson (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Jackson, Samuel C. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Johns, Barbara (Powell) (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Kelly, Alfred H. (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Kiene, Thomas (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Kirk, Grayson (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Korman, Milton (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Kreech, David (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Lawson, Belford, and Marjorie (McKenzie) (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Lawson, Henry (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Levinson, Harry (M.D.) (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Lewis, Anthony (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Lovett, Edward P. (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - McIlwaine, T.J. (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - McKay, Ellis H. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Marshall, Thurgood (Box 4, Folder 65-67)
    - Meagher, William R. (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Meltsner, Michael (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Menninger, Karl (M.D.) (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Micrum, George B., III (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Minton, Sherman (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Modlin, George M. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Montgomery, Eugene (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Moon, Henry Lee (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Nabrit, James M., Jr. (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Nabrit, James N., III (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Newman, Roger (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Odum, Howard (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Oliver, William W. (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Parker, John J. (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Paul, James C.N. (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Pearson, Conrad O. (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Peattie, Lisa R. (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Perry, Marian Wynn (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Pollak, Louis (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Pollock, Earl E. (Box 5, Folder 102-103)
    - Poston, Ted (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Prettyman, E. Barrett, Jr. (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Randall, Robert L. (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Rankin, J. Lee (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Redding, Louis J. (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Redfield, Margaret P. (Box 10, Folder 155)
    - Reed, Stanley (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Rehnquist, William H. (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Reich, Charles (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Reily, John W. (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Rhodes, Richard L. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Roberts, Chalmers M. (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Robertson, Archibald G. (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Robinson, Spottswood W., III (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Rogers, S.E. (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Rogers, William D. (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Ross, Merrill (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Rowe, Frederick (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Rubenstein, Ernest (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Ryan, James R. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Sander, Frank E.A. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Scott, Charles (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Scott, John (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Seitz, Collins J. (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Smith, Wayne A. (Box 4, Folder 65-67)
    - Steel, Lewis M. (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Stoval, Alice (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Taylor, William L. (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Tidwell, Winfred (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Thompson, Charles H. (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Timmerman, George Bell (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Todd, Lucinda (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Troubh, Ray (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Vinson, Fred M., and Fred M. Vinson, Jr. (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Vorenberg, James (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Waddy, Joseph C. (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Wadsworth, Homer C. (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Wallace, Harry L. (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Waring, Julius Waties (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Warren, Earl (Box 5, Folder 102-103)
    - Wechsler, Herbert (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Weinstein, Jack B. (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Wertham, Fredric (M.D.) (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Whipple, Taggart (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Whitehead, Matthew (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Wilkins, Roy (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Williams, Franklin (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Williams, Mamie (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Wilson, Paul (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Wimmer, James R. (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Workman, W.D. (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Place and Event Files
    - Afro-American Newspapers (Box 4, Folder 65-67)
    - Civil Rights (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Delaware (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - "Adolescent Negro Education in Delaware," by George R. Miller, Jr. (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Desegregation (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Desegregation (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - District of Columbia (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Education (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Howard University (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Howard Conference, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Kansas (Box 12, Folder 124-125)
    - Margold Report (Nathan Margold) (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - NAACP (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - National mood (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Negroes (Box 13, Folder 129)
    - Personalities in case (non-Supreme Court) (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - Prince Edward County supplementary data (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - South Carolina (Box 14, Folder 132)
    - South Carolina - Clarendon County supplementary data (Box 14, Folder 133)
    - Supreme Court (Box 14, Folder 134)
    - Virginia (Box 15, Folder 135-136)
- NAACP Legal Defense Fund Correspondence, Series II
  This series consists entirely of photocopies or carbon copies of correspondence from the files of the NAACP Legal Defense Fund. The correspondence is arranged roughly in chronological order and has been numbered by Kluger as a key to a descriptive list which precedes the correspondence. The correspondence itself is very valuable to the researcher because it outlines the legal strategy employed by the NAACP in its fight to end segregation in the public school systems in the United States.
  - Topeka #1-341 (Box 9, Folder 137)
  - Clarendon #342-554 (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Office #555-699, 1951 January 14 - 1953 January 6 (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - Office #700-1007 Reargument, 1953 July 8 - 1955 April 8 (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Amicus Curiae - Delaware #1008-1165, 1951 September 6 - 1959 March 19 (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 142)
- Court Transcripts and Law Review Articles, Series III
  This series consists largely of photocopied transcripts and briefs; some official transcripts; a book; two papers by individuals other than Kluger, which provide background information; and three folders of Law Review articles dealing with segregation. Kluger states in "Sources and Acknowledgements" that these transcripts and briefs were the "most basic" materials in his research and that "assembling the legal record in the lower courts was a considerable project in itself." The researcher is saved a great deal of time and effort by having these transcripts and briefs collected together in this series.
  - Brown: case and some briefs (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - Brown: Kansas and U.S. government brief (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - Briggs vs. Elliott: October term 1951 (Box 10, Folder 145)
  - Briggs vs. Elliott: October term 1952 (Box 10, Folder 146)
  - Briggs vs. Elliott: October term 1953 (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - "The Background of the Abandonment of Reconstruction" by C. Vann Woodward (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - School Segregation Cases: Proposed Appendix to Appelants' Briefs by Howard Jay Graham (Box 10, Folder 149)
  - Davis vs. County School Board of Prince Edward County, Virginia (Box 10, Folder 150-151)
  - Bolling vs. Sharpe (Box 10, Folder 152)
  - Gebhart vs. Belding (Box 10, Folder 153)
  - Argument, edited by Leon Friedman (Box 10, Folder 154)
  - Sweatt, other pre-Brown decisions, and chronology of civil rights cases (Box 10A, Folder 155)
  - Law reviews (Box 11, Folder 156-158)
- Sources and Additional Research Materials, Series IV
  This series includes a section from Kluger's book, "Sources and Acknowledgements," which calls attention to the relative importance of the different materials in the collection. It also provides the researcher with a list of interviewees; the date or dates on which they were interviewed and their relationship to the case; a research bibliography; a table of cases cited; and chapter notes to the book. The second section of the series contains "A Short History of Education in the United States" and A Long History of Negro Education, both by Phyllis Kluger. The final section of the series contains two folders of photocopied journal articles discussing legal, social and historic aspects of the segregation cases.
  - "Sources and Acknowledgements" by Richard Kluger (Box 11, Folder 159)
  - Writings of Phyllis Kluger
    - "A Short History of Education in the United States" (Box 11, Folder 160)
    - A Long History of Negro Education (pp 1-80) (Box 11, Folder 161)
    - A Long History of Negro Education (pp 81-160) (Box 11, Folder 162)
    - A Long History of Negro Education (pp 161-240) (Box 11, Folder 163)
    - A Long History of Negro Education (pp 241-320) (Box 11, Folder 164)
    - A Long History of Negro Education (pp 321-400) (Box 11, Folder 165)
    - A Long History of Negro Education (pp 401-480) (Box 11, Folder 166)
    - A Long History of Negro Education (pp 481-568) (Box 11, Folder 167)
  - Journal Articles
    - Journal of Negro Education Articles (legal) (Box 11, Folder 168)
    - Journal of Negro Education Articles (Box 11, Folder 169)